Finding Aid for William T. Brownson papers, 1949-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William T. Brownson papers 1949-1975
Brownson, William T.
0.5 linear feet
8549 Aa 2
Labor relations specialist for the Lamar Pipe Company and the Michigan Concrete Pipe Association. Materials relating to his dealings with the Teamster's union; also papers concerning his work with an Ann Arbor, Michigan, citizens group formed to oppose proposed building on Stadium Blvd.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by William T. Brownson (Donor no. 5756 ) in September 1975.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William T. Brownson started his career as a labor relations specialist and union negotiator at the Jackson Concrete Pipe Company in Jackson, Michigan (ca. 1949), where he handled contract negotiations on behalf of management. Around 1953, the company was bought out by the American Marietta Company and was renamed the Lamar Pipe and Tile Company. However, Brownson retained his position and continued as the official liaison between the new company and the Teamsters Union.
In the early days of unionization within the concrete pipe industry, Brownson quickly moved up the ranks, becoming more influential as the years passed. He was chairman of the Labor Negotiation Committee and later, secretary of the Concrete Pipe Association (a consortium of companies).
During this period of wage, benefit, and rule standardization, Brownson's activities as labor specialist were very much intertwined with that of top union officials, high-level management in the concrete pipe industry, and attorneys. Thus, his papers cannot be separated from those of the other key players in the constant give-and-take of contract negotiation.
The other major activity Brownson was involved in was as chairman of an Ann Arbor citizens' rights group called the New Southeast Property Owners Committee (hereafter referred to as "NSPOC"), formed in 1957. The group was opposed to the commercial development of the area between Stadium Boulevard and Winchell Drive in Ann Arbor. The NSPOC believed that the City Council had taken improper action when it rezoned the area from residential to commercial and lobbied heavily to get it changed to prevent the developer who bought the land from ever building his proposed shopping center. Brownson and the NSPOC's main concern was with the changing character of a residential neighborhood, with increased traffic posing a threat to the safety of the residents' children. Ultimately, however, they were unsuccessful in their opposition to commercial development in their neighborhood.
The William T. Brownson Papers comprise two series: Labor and Union (1949-75) and the New Southeast Property Owners Committee (1957-59). The second series offers a valuable look at how a local citizens' group fought organized government and corporate developers.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.).; Brownson, William T.; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America.; Industrial relations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Land use--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Concrete Pipe Association.; Citizens' associations--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Streets.; Arborland (Shopping mall: Ann Arbor, Mich.); Brownson, William T.; Shopping malls--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Stadium Boulevard (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Streets--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Labor and Union, 1949-1975
  The Labor and Union series documents Brownson's work as a labor specialist and union negotiator on behalf of the concrete pipe industry. The papers are arranged chronologically by year, although not every year is represented as contracts were renegotiated every three years. Within each folder, the papers are also arranged chronologically, with undated material at the end of each folder. In this series, there are mainly printed copies of contracts and correspondence. Much of the correspondence is not from or to Brownson, but nevertheless documents the process of contract negotiation and thus, his activities, if only indirectly. This series, therefore, is most valuable if seen as a contribution to the history of labor-management relations, as collected by Brownson, rather than a documentation of Brownson's career. Photographs of an unidentified Lamar Pipe and Tile Company plant can be found at the end of the 1960 folder.
  - 1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - 1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958 (Box 1)
  - 1960 (Box 1)
    (includes photographs)
  - 1961 (Box 1)
  - 1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963 (Box 1)
  - 1965 (Box 1)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
- New Southeast Property Owners Committee, 1957-1959
  The New Southeast Property Owners Committee (NSPOC) series documents the efforts of a grassroots organization to prevent commercial development of a shopping center in a formerly residential neighborhood. The series is divided by categories of documents (e.g. reports, clippings, etc.) but not arranged in any particular order therein, except for the correspondence, which is in chronological order. The Reports file contains three different types of reports: 1) those written by the NSPOC, 2) a consulting firm's report which the NSPOC commissioned, and 3) a report by the Ann Arbor Planning Commission, an advisory arm of the City Council. The reports the NSPOC generated to send out are the most informative in terms of why they formed a group in the first place, how they functioned, and how they presented their case to the public. The Hearings and Petitions file is also helpful in understanding exactly what the group's concerns were. In terms of visual materials, there are blueprints of Arborland and one of an unnamed shopping center as well as photographs of the initial groundwork of Arborland (ca. 1957).
  - Reports (Box 1)
  - Hearings and Petitions (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Legal Documents (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Blueprints and Map (Arborland and unnamed shopping center) (Box 1)
  - Photographs (construction of Arborland), ca. 1957 (Box 1)